(ナルト)夢だって ちゃんとある。
I've got dreams too!
I'm gonna become an even greater
Hokage than you, Dad!
俺ってば
父ちゃんを超す火影になる！
ぜってえなるからな。
I swear I will!
あっちで母ちゃんにも伝えてくれ。
So when you see Mom over there,
please tell her…
俺のことは
全然 心配なんかすんなって。
that she doesn't have to
worry about me at all!
しっかり やってんだって！
Tell her I'm doin' my best!
THE FINAL VALLEY
(ヒルゼン)あとのことは任せたぞ。
We're leaving the rest to you…
Kakashi, Sakura…
カカシ サクラ サスケ ナルト…。
Sasuke and Naruto.
(カカシ)三代目。
Lord Third!
(扉間)兄者
これで マダラとの決着もついた。
Elder Brother, you finally
settled things with Madara.
あとは サルの言うように
ただ後の者どもに託すとしよう。
As Saru said…
let's leave the rest
to the next generation.
《柱間 : うずまきナルト。
Naruto Uzumaki…
うちはサスケ。
Sasuke Uchiha…
お前たちなら 俺たちとは違う
決着もあるだろう。
You two will probably find
a different conclusion than we did.
いや そうなってくれ》
No…make sure you do.
(孫悟空)
これで俺たちは もう自由だ。
Now, we're free too!
俺は水簾洞に帰るで ウキキィー！
I'm going back to Suirendo!
I'm going to seclude myself in a forest.
(穆王)
私は森にこもることにします。
We can finally go back to our homes.
(重明)
やっと俺らも故郷へ帰れんだな。
It's like a dream.
なんか夢見てるみてえだぜ。
(九喇嘛)
八尾 てめえはどうすんだ？
Eight Tails, what are you gonna do?
Me? Well…
(牛鬼)俺か？ 俺はだな…。
やっぱ
ビーのところへ戻ることにする。
I think I'm gonna go back to Bee.
あいつの耳障りなラップも
クセになっちまってるしな。
Even his annoying rap
has ended up growing on me.
で お前は？
ん？
So, what about you?
どうすんだよ？
What will you do?
俺はなぁ…。
I'll…
(ハゴロモ)お前たち全員のチャクラは→
A little piece of each of your chakra…
すでに ナルトの中に
少しずつ入っている。
is already within Naruto.
ナルトは いわばお前たちの
寄り合い所みたいなものだ。
In short, Naruto is like
a gathering place for you.
If you want to discuss something,
何か相談事があれば→
you can speak to each other through
your chakra inside Naruto.
ナルトの中のチャクラで
おのおの話し合える。
九喇嘛。
ん？
Kurama…
Hmm?
I'd like you to stay inside Naruto as
the overseer of the gathering place.
お前は寄り合い所の管理役として
ナルトの中にいてやれ。
えっ！
もう 苦ではなかろう。
It's no longer a hardship
for you anymore, is it?
ま じじいがそう言うなら
しかたねえか。
Well, if you say so, old man,
I guess have no choice.
(みんな)ハハハハ！
何だ!? 何がおかしい！
What?!
What's so funny?
素直でないところは
相変わらずですね 九喇嘛。
Still not upfront with your feelings…
You haven't changed at all, Kurama.
ヘヘヘッ。
(サクラ)これでやっと
忍界大戦は終わったんですね。
So the Great Ninja War
is finally over now.
あぁ あとは…。
Yes. All that's left is…
ナルトとサスケ
前に わしが問うたな。
Naruto and Sasuke…
I asked you before.
我が母 カグヤと戦い→
After battling my mother Kaguya,
己の出した答えに
変化はあったか？
is there any change to
the answers you gave me?
答えは変わんねえ。
My answer's the same.
ただ 大じいちゃんには悪いけど→
And I'm sorry, Super Gramps,
今回 カグヤってのと戦って思った。
but there is one thing I feel
strongly about after fighting Kaguya…
俺の母ちゃんが
うずまきクシナで心底よかったって。
I'm really glad that
Kushina Uzumaki was my mom.
カグヤは
今まで戦ったやつらとは違う。
Kaguya was different from
anyone I've ever battled.
心が ねえみてえな感じだった。
It's like she didn't have a heart at all.
母カグヤも 初めは
民の信望厚き女神だったそうだ。
It's said my mother Kaguya started off
as a beloved goddess of the people.
鬼と呼ばれるように変貌した
理由はわからぬが…。
I do not know for sure what
caused her to transform
into a being that came to
be called a demon.
おそらくチャクラの実を
食らったときから→
I suspect something was triggered
the moment she devoured
the Chakra Fruit.
何かが始まっていたのだろう。
どちらにしろ お前は母とは違う。
In any case,
you are not like my mother.
尾獣たちすべてのチャクラを
有していても→
I trust you not to become like her,
母のようにはなるまいて。
even with all of the Tailed Beast
Chakra within you.
さて 残るは
無限月読を解術するだけだ。
Now then, all that's left is…
to undo the Infinite Tsukuyomi.
But how, specifically?
Do you need our powers?
具体的にはどうやる？
わしたちの力も必要なのか？
お前たちはいい。
No, you're fine.
Naruto has the chakra
of every Tailed Beast.
尾獣すべてのチャクラを持つナルトと→
And Sasuke possesses the Rinnegan.
輪廻眼を持つサスケが
互いに子の印を結びさえすれば→
If they both weave
the sign for rat simultaneously,
術は完全に解ける。
the jutsu will be undone.
What? That's it? It's so simple.
なんだ 意外と簡単じゃねえか。
I researched thoroughly how to
undo Mother's Infinite Tsukuyomi.
かつて母がやった無限月読を
解術するために調べ尽くした。
間違いない。
There's no mistake.
Now then,
the rest is up to you, Sasuke.
して あとは サスケよ。 お前は？
(サスケ)そうだな。
だが まずは この無限月読の中→
Yes…
But first, I'm executing the current
Five Kage inside the Infinite Tsukuyomi.
今の五影どもを処刑する。
今 なんて言った サスケ？
え？
What did you just say, Sasuke?
五影を… なんだと？
What about the Five Kage?
それとな 尾獣ども→
Oh, and…
I'm putting all of you Tailed Beasts
under my control…
お前らはすべて
俺の管理下に置き→
and eventually,
I'll get rid of you as well.
いずれ処理する。
なんだと！
What did you say?!
グッ ウッ…。
九喇嘛！
Kurama!
He put the Tailed Beasts
in a genjutsu…
尾獣たちを幻術に…。
ただの一瞥で…。
and with a single glance too.
Naruto, it has ended up
as I expected.
ナルトよ やはり こうなったな。
あとは
お前に任せるしかなくなった。
I have no choice
but to leave the rest to you.
I cannot stay in
this world any longer.
わしも この世にいる限界だ。
じきに消える。
I shall soon fade away.
Yeah, and sorry for saying this,
Six Paths Super Gramps…
ああ。 これも六道の
大じいちゃんには悪いけど→
大じいちゃんの
子供らみてえにはならねえよ。
but we won't end up like your sons.
俺はアシュラじゃねえ。
I'm not Ashura.
And Sasuke isn't Indra either.
それに サスケは
インドラってやつでもねえ！
Sasuke!
Is this what your current dream is?
サスケ それが
今のお前の夢だってのか！
まだお前は復讐を
望んでいるっていうのか？
Are you saying you're
still seeking vengeance?
サスケ君！
Sasuke!
I admit, at one time,
all I wished for was destruction,
確かに かつては ただ破壊を望み
復讐だけが目的だった。
and vengeance was my goal.
But I feel differently now.
だが今は違う。
破壊し そして創り直すのさ。
I want to destroy, and rebuild.
闇を抱えぬ里。 忍世界を一新する。
A village no longer
shrouded in darkness.
I'll reform the shinobi world.
グッ…。
What I'm touting is…
俺が掲げるもの それは…。
革命だ！
革命… だと？
…revolution!
Revolution?!
My dear Sasuke,
what do you want to do?
((サスケよ お前は何がしたい？
この戦いの果てに 何を望む？
What is it that you seek
in the aftermath of this war?
I want to hear your honest thoughts
and opinions.
(お前の正直な考えを聞きたい))
((今までの影たちが
この状況を作った。
All of the previous Kage created
these current circumstances.
So I will become Hokage
and change the village.
(だから俺が火影になり
里を変える))
This Hokage you speak of…
What do you mean by it?
((そのお前のいう火影とは
どういう意味だ？
(そんなに知りたきゃ教えてやる))
If want to know so badly,
I'll tell you.
Catastrophic Planetary Devastation!
地爆天星！
あぁっ！
Naruto…
It's on you!
ナルト… 頼む！
I swear
I'll get you all out!
俺が 必ず 助け出す！
Just hang in there
a little while longer!
少しの間 辛抱してくれ！
Because of this war,
この戦争で 輪廻眼の能力と
使い方も ずいぶんと慣れた。
I've become quite adept at
using my Rinnegan's abilities.
そして 邪魔者は いなくなった。
And all those who were
in my way are gone.
お前以外はな！ ナルト。
Except for you…
Naruto.
Things just don't go as planned.
(ハゴロモ)うまく いかぬものだ。
力を一方に託した結果が
かつての インドラとアシュラ…。
When I bequeathed power
to just one side,
I ended up with Indra and Ashura.
This time, even after entrusting power
to both, the result is the same.
そして 両方に託した結果も
今や 同じ…。
ふぅ…。
Nope… All sibling squabbling
ends right here!
いや 兄弟ゲンカは
ここで 終わりにするってばよ。
Let the Tailed Beasts go.
They've finally gained freedom.
尾獣たちを放してやってくれ。
あいつらは
やっと 自由になれたんだ。
あいつらと仲よくなったから
わかんだ。
I'm friends with them, so I know.
They won't cause trouble anymore.
もう 悪さはしねえよ。
ナルト！
お前 わかってないようだな。
Naruto, you don't seem to get it.
You're now the Jinchuriki
of all the Tailed Beasts.
今や お前は
尾獣たち全員の人柱力だ。
Which means I plan to
eventually get rid of
もちろん
お前の中の尾獣のチャクラも→
のちのち すべて
始末するつもりだ。
the Tailed Beast Chakra
inside of you too.
そんな…。
What?!
つまり お前は死ぬんだ ナルト。
In other words,
you're going to die, Naruto.
必然的にな。
Out of necessity.
仙人が言ったとおりなら
無限月読を解くのに→
If what the Sage said was true,
there's no need to use
そもそも お前の中の尾獣の力を
使う必要はないだろ。
the Tailed Beast power inside you
to release the Infinite Tsukuyomi.
I can take advantage of
the Tailed Beasts that I captured.
俺が捕まえた尾獣どもを
利用すればな…。
やつらも それまでは
生かしておいてやる。
I'll let them live until then.
You know that I won't
let you do that, right?
俺が そうさせねえの
わかってるよな？
やはり… まずは お前か ナルト。
I guess I'll have to
deal with you first, Naruto.
場所を変える。
Let's move this elsewhere.
You know, don't you?
お前なら わかっているな？
(カカシ)待て サスケ！
Wait, Sasuke!
うぅ…。
先生！
Sensei!
《写輪眼の影響が まだ…》
The lingering aftereffects
of the Sharingan…
I…
私は！ 私にはどうすることも
できないって本当はわかってる。
I know in my heart that
there's nothing I can do!
大好きなのに サスケ君を
こんなに思ってるのに。
Even though I love you.
Even though I care about you
so much, Sasuke. And yet…
寄り添うことも
刺し違えることもできずに→
I can't get close to you
or exchange blows with you.
こうやって また駄々こねて
泣くことしかできない。
I can only whine and beg
and cry like this again.
みっともないよね ほんと。
It's so pitiful, isn't it?
((サクラ…。
Sakura…
(ありがとう))
Thank you.
But…But Sasuke!
でも でも サスケ君！
If there's even a little corner of
your heart that thinks about me,
少しでも 少しでも私のことが
心の隅っこにあるなら→
お願い
もう遠くに行かないで！
please don't leave again!
If we stick together,
I know it can be like old times again…
ずっと一緒にいれば
いつか 昔みたいに…。
お前は 本当にうざいな。
You're…
…really annoying.
サクラ！
Sakura!
You didn't need to put Sakura
under genjutsu!
サクラちゃんに幻術まで
かけることはねえだろうが。
If I didn't,
このままじゃ こいつは
俺たちを追ってくるだろう。
she would've chased after us,
and gotten in the way.
邪魔になる。
サクラは サクラはお前を
助けたかったんだ ずっと。
Sakura…Sakura just wanted
to help you, all this time.
恋愛ごっこでも楽しめってのか？
So you're suggesting
I enjoy a little romance?
俺には こいつを好く道理も
好かれる道理もない。
Well, I have no reason to love her
or be loved by her.
理由があるのは
人を嫌いになるときだけでいい。
The only time you need a reason
is when you hate someone!
それにサクラは今 お前を
自分のものにしたいんじゃない。
And Sakura's not trying to
make you hers!
ただ お前を助けたいんだ。
She just wants to help you!
お前に殺されかけたこともある
この子が→
She almost died
by your hand.
今でもお前のことを思い
涙を流すのは→
But she still thinks of your welfare
and sheds tears for you…
お前を愛して苦しんでいるからだ。
because she suffers from loving you!
((母さん。
ん？
Mom…
父さんは兄さんや俺のこと
本当はどう思ってんのかな？
How does Dad really feel
about Big Brother and me?
どうしたの？ 急に。
What makes you ask that
out of the blue?
この前 父さん俺のことを→
The other day, he said to me,
"That's my boy."
さすが 俺の子だって
言ってくれたんだ。
いつもは兄さんに
そう言ってたから→
He usually says that to Big Brother,
so I was really happy.
すごい嬉しかったんだ。
そう よかったじゃない。
Is that so? That's nice.
でも最近 父さんと兄さんの
仲がよくないから…。
But recently, Dad and Big Brother
haven't been getting along, so…
俺は ただ兄さんの
代わりなのかなって。
I thought maybe I'm just
a stand-in for Big Brother…
兄さんは兄さん
あなたは あなたよ。
Your brother is your brother,
and you are you.
父さんは いつも
あなたたちのことを→
Your father is always
thinking about the both of you.
心配しているわ。
じゃあ なんで兄さんばっかり。
Then why is it always
about Big Brother?!
そうじゃないわ ただ父さんはね→
That's not the case.
Your father represents our clan,
一族の代表として うちは一族を→
and he's expected to
protect the Uchiha Clan.
守らなきゃいけない立場にあるの。
So what?
それがなんなの？
It's just that Itachi is older than you,
and your senior.
イタチは あなたより
大きくて先輩なだけ。
その分 一族のための仕事を
任されるようになるでしょ。
So he's given more duties
relating to the clan.
父さんは
その仕事の監督役だから→
Since your father
oversees those duties,
どうしたって その目が イタチに→
it's only natural that his eyes
will be more focused on Itachi.
いきがちだったのかも
しれないわね。
でも ここだけの話→
But this is just between us…
私と話すときは
あなたのことばかり→
When your father is with me,
all he talks about is you.
話してるのよ 父さん。
ただ あの人→
He's always so serious,
いつも
ムスッとして 不器用だからね。
and just not very good at
expressing his feelings.
はい サスケ お弁当。
Here's your lunch, Sasuke.
手裏剣のお稽古なら→
When you come home,
I'll watch over your shuriken practice.
帰ってから
母さんが見てあげるから。
お稽古じゃない 修業だよ。
It's not practice. It's training.
I'm leaving!
(いってきます。
いってらっしゃい))
Have a great day.
それが
失敗した過去の縛りなのかもな。
Perhaps, those are the ties
to a failed past.
《サスケ…》
Sasuke!
約束したんだ。
I made a promise.
昔 サクラちゃんと。
Long ago…to Sakura.
((サスケは ぜってぇ
俺が連れて帰る。
I'll definitely bring Sasuke back!
(一生の約束だってばよ))
I swear on my life!
先生 俺の忍道は
もう知ってんだろ？
Sensei! You know about
my Ninja Way, right?
行ってくっぜ。
I'm gonna go.
ああ 頼んだぞ。
Yeah… We're counting on you.
(ハゴロモ)愛情とは難しいものだな。
Love is a difficult thing…
かつて わしにも
２人の子がいた。
I once had two sons.
２人を愛し
２人もわしを敬愛していた。
I loved them both,
and they loved and revered me.
But I entrusted everything
to the younger brother.
だが兄弟の弟だけに
すべてを託したゆえ→
それを機に 兄はわしと
その弟を憎むようになり→
That became the impetus
for the older brother to begin
hating his brother and me.
愛情が憎しみへと
変わってしまったのだ。
Love transformed into hate.
今のサスケを形作ったのは→
What molded the current Sasuke,
過去の愛情の
喪失からくるものに他ならない。
is none other than
his loss of love in the past.
マダラも そうだった。
Madara was the same too.
サスケも マダラと同じ運命だと
そうおっしゃりたいのですか？
Are you saying that Sasuke shares
the same fate as Madara?
そうではない
わしも己なりに→
No, not at all.
I, too, want to make the future
better in my own way.
未来は
よりよいものにしたいのだ。
かつての過ちから学んでな。
Having learned from past mistakes,
this time I gave both of them the power.
今回は２人に
同じように力を託した。
The past does not exist
過去は 未来が変わらぬと→
to remind the present that
the future cannot change.
気づかせるために
あるのではなく→
未来のためにあるはずだ。
The past is supposed to exist
for the sake of the future.
なぜ ナルトに
可能性を見いだしたのです？
How did you see the potential
within Naruto?
うずまきナルト。
Naruto Uzumaki…
The boy was able to save
and befriend Kurama,
あの子は
憎しみの塊になってしまった→
九喇嘛を救い 友となった男だ。
who had become
a concretion of hatred.
ナルトに任せてみるとしよう。
I shall let Naruto handle this.
今度は 憎しみが
愛情へと変わるのを願いながら。
Since I hope that hate can be
transformed into love this time.
いや 愛情を
取り戻させると願おう。
Or rather, I have hope that
love can be regained.
Because, unlike my mother,
Naruto as well as Sasuke…
(ハゴロモ)サスケも カグヤとは違い
愛が何かを知っている者だ。
ナルトと同じようにな。
know what love is.
やっぱここかよ
懐かしいな サスケ。
This place, huh?
I should've figured.
Doesn't it bring back memories,
Sasuke?
昔 ここでやり合ったな
そういやよ。
Long ago, we fought here.
前と同じだ
ここでまたお前が負ける。
And just like before,
you're going to lose.
You won't be hitting me with
that same punch as last time!
あのときと同じ拳は
もうくらわねえよ。
それに お前の好き勝手には
させねえ。
I'm not about to let you get away
with whatever you want.
火影だって
お前にゃ渡せねえ。
I won't let you become
the Hokage, either!
お前は 火影がなんなのか
まるでわかってねえ。
You don't even understand
what it means to be Hokage!
言ったな 革命だと。
I told you, that to me,
being Hokage means revolution.
俺の言う火影は
お前のそれと まったく違う。
It's totally different from what you think.
お前の兄ちゃんが言ったことを
教えてやる。
火影ってのは→
火影になったやつが
認められるんじゃなく→
みんなに認められたやつが
火影になるんだってよ。
俺はイタチの言葉ではなく
生き様からすべてを悟った。
お前と俺では
出した答えが違う。
戦う前に はっきりさせるか。
俺の言う火影とは何なのか
教えてやる。